In 1991, Linus Torvalds created the Linux
kernel as an open source software project
where changes to the software were passed
as patches and archived files. Now this
was done for a little over a decade, until
in 2002 the Linux project began using a
proprietary distributed version control
system called BitKeeper. Now this worked
out well, as it brought the advantages of
a distributed version control system to
the Linux kernel, and at the time, it
allowed open source developers to use the
basic version for free. But since
BitKeeper is a proprietary software, many
of the Linux developers were against the
idea of using a proprietary software for
contributing to Linux's open source
kernel. And in 2005, BitKeeper decided to
revoke its free-of-charge status for using
the tool. Not wanting to revert to their
previous model of using patches, this
change prompted Linus Torvalds and the
Linux development community to develop
their own tool based on the advantages of
BitKeeper. Now, they wanted a tool that
would be fast, have a simple and
easy-to-use design, have strong support
for non-linear development, be fully
distributed, and be able to handle large
projects with efficiency. The tool that
was created was called Git. Now, since its
birth in 2005, Git has retained these
initial qualities as it has evolved and
matured to be the popular distributed
version control system that it has today,
that so many developers, team members,
project managers, and project
collaborators choose for their projects.
Now that we're familiar with the different
types of version control systems, and why
Git was created, let's now look a little
closer and understand exactly how Git works.